Alex Bair

PROFILE

I'm a full stack software engineer with extensive experience in JavaScript, TypeScript, and Ruby. I leverage my engineering and project management backgrounds to deconstruct complex problems and drive them to resolution. When I'm not at the computer, I bake (usually tasty) cookies and lift (not usually heavy) weights.

EXPERIENCE

Creator, Software Engineer, Willow

2024 - present

Willow (willow-cdc.github.io) is an open-source framework for creating change data capture pipelines. It reflects database changes to a cache in near real-time.

- Reduced pipeline creation from 9 steps to 4 steps.
- Designed and constructed a custom connector to transform events from Kafka and send to a cache (KafkaJS).
- Resolved Debezium configuration issues preventing multiple pipelines from connecting to the same database.
- Ensured Willow functions when provided a minimum privileged database user, avoiding the need to provide Willow with superuser privileges.
- Architected and implemented a RESTful API, facilitating pipeline creation and teardown (Express).
- Built pipeline management UI (React, Material UI).
- Authored comprehensive technical case study (willow-cdc.github.io/case-study ☑).

Software Engineer, Self-employed

2022 - 2024

Developed freelance and open-source applications including:

- Whirlpool Tool for collecting and debugging webhooks (DO Droplet, Nginx, Express, Socket.io).
- Media Watchlist A media tracking web app (Ruby, Sinatra, PostgreSQL, HTML/CSS).

Project Management Specialist, Merck

2019 - 2022

Led cross-functional teams on a \$46MM capital project portfolio to increase vaccine supply capacity.

Photolithography Process Engineer, Texas Instruments

2017 - 2019

Developed detection/interdiction systems using in-house technologies, reducing material holds by 30%.

SKILLS

BackendNode.js, Ruby, Golang, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, RESTful APIs, Express, Sinatra, Minitest, Redis, KafkaJS

FrontendJavaScript (ES6+), TypeScript, HTML, CSS, React, Jest, Handlebars

Other

Git/GitHub, Docker, Linux, Bash, Apache Kafka, Debezium, Nginx, Object Oriented Programming

EDUCATION

Launch School 2022 – 2024

Multi-year, mastery-based software engineering curriculum. Read more at launchschool.com/employers 🗵

Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology

2013 - 2017